hey y push students here's period 9 in
just 3
[Music]
minutes period 9 starts in 1980 with the
election of Ronald Reagan between the
Iranian hostage crisis and a wave of
conservativism Republican Ronald Reagan
won the presidency in the election of
1980 his campaign focused on shrinking
the size of the federal government
decreasing spending and supply side
economics which is known as Reaganomics
but while Reagan decreased spending by
cutting Great Society programs he
increased defense spending for example
he supported the Strategic Defense
Initiative which is also known as Star
Wars in the ongoing arms race with the
Soviet Union but Reaganomics was
criticized because corporations in the
wealthy benefited from his tax cuts
while many argued these benefits failed
to trickle down to the working class
Reagan was also criticized for his role
in the Iran Contra affair but most of
Reagan's foreign policy was focused on
ending the Cold War he and Gorbachev
focused on more diplomatic Solutions
including his famous speech at the
Berlin Wall ultimately the Cold War
ended in 1991 under President George HW
Bush with the fall of the Berlin wall
and the collapse of the Soviet Union for
the remainder of period 9 foreign policy
is focused on the growing crisis in the
Middle East for example President Bush
sent American forces into Kuwait during
the Gulf War which is also known as
Operation Desert Storm the goal was to
prevent further aggression from Saddam
Hussein the Iraqi leader who had invaded
Kuwait and in 2001 President George W
bush announced a war on terror following
the September 11th 2001 attacks on the
World Trade Center American forces were
dispatched in operation Iraqi freedom
and operation enduring freedom to combat
terrorism remove Saddam Hussein from
power and to capture Osama Bin Laden
meanwhile domestic policy in period 9 is
dominated by increasing political
polarization since 1980 the Democrat and
Republican parties have intensely
debated issues like federal spending and
immigration policies as well as social
issues like abortion and gay marriage
and the parties argued over how the
federal government should respond to
National crises like the Great Recession
and the covid-19 pandemic migration and
immigration are also a big part of
period 9 the Midwest which was once
known as the steel belt transformed into
the Rust Belt because of a decline in
manufacturing and overseas competition
and international migration from Latin
America and from Asia increased
dramatically which led to political
debates and an increase in nativism the
new immigrants influenced American
culture and supplied the economy with an
important labor force and the final
topic of period 9 is globalization with
new technologies like personal computers
the Internet cell phones and social
media the world is more interconnected
than ever economies are also connected
through groups like The World Trade
Organization and the North American free
trade agreement so to bring us full
circle globalization is like the Clum
exchange that we talked about in period
1 it brings people goods and ideas
closer together and it aims to grow
Global economies through increased trade
new Industries and new markets thanks
for watching and if you want more aush
helps like study guides timelines and
summary videos make sure you check out
the ultimate review packet